After looking at Lamport's bakery algorithm,
let's move to a slightly different problem, that
of the readers and writers. In this case, we have
multiple entities accessing a shared resource, but
such entities are of different types and we have
different safety properties associated with them.
Both writers and readers are trying to access
a shared resource, for instance, a file.
Only one writer at the time
can write to such a resource.
Multiple readers are allowed to read at the
same time, but not concurrently with writers.
We are going to look at how we can solve this
synchronization problem using semaphores.
If we try to visualize the
dependencies between the
entry and exit sections of writers
and readers, it looks like this.
For the writer, the entry section needs to
wait until no one accesses the shared object.
Once the critical section is over (i.e.,
the portion in which the writer writes to
the shared resource), the exit section can
send a signal about the fact that no one is
accessing the object anymore, and such a signal
can be consumed by both a writer or a reader.
For the reader, the entry section
should first check if the reader
is the first reader of a batch of readers
that tries to access the shared resource.
If that is the case, then the reader should
wait. If other readers are already accessing
the resource, then the reader can
simply enter its critical section.
For the exit section, the reader should of
course inform others it is done with its
critical section. If the reader was the only one /
the last one completing its critical section, then
a signal should be sent for writers or for another
batch of readers to enter their critical section.
Let's now look at the pseudocode that uses
semaphores according to these dependencies.
We have writers and readers
sharing the following variables:
- two binary semaphores, noone_accesses and
protect_check (notice that both are initially 1),
and
- rc,
readers counter, which is initially set to 0.
The writers simply protect their critical
section by waiting on the noone_accesses variable
(entry section) and sending a signal
on the same variable (exit section).
The readers use the protect_check variable to
make sure they consistently update the rc value.
In the entry section, the first reader
that manages to increase it to 1 (i.e.,
the first reader of a batch) also waits on
the noone_accesses variable (to
synchronize with the writers).
In the exit section, the reader that sets rc
to 0 (notice access to rc is also synchronized
here using the protect_check variable among
readers) also signals on the noone_accesses
variable, so that a writer or another batch of
readers can then enter the critical section.
As before, I suggest you try to have some formal
reasoning about how this solution is correct,
at least in terms of mutual
exclusion and progress.
If you think about fairness, you can probably see
that here readers are privileged over writers.
Once a reader increases rc to 1, other readers can
keep accessing their critical section an unbounded
number of times. As long as rc is not set back
to 0, writers cannot access the shared resource.